in this video we're going to focus on
some problems dealing with the single
sit diffraction experiment
but let's review some things that was
mentioned in the video i created for
young's double slit experiment
so here we have a double slit separated
by distance d
and here's the screen
l is the distance between the slits and
the screen
now for a double slit experiment
at the middle you have a large
bright fringe
and then the amplitude of the bright
fringes decreases progressively
and so m would be 0 here this
m is 1
and m is 2 for the bright fringes
accordingly
so that's if we have
a double slit experiment
and there's three equations that was
mentioned
this one d sine theta
is equal to m lambda that's the first
one you need to know
a second equation that was derived was
this one
y is equal to
l tangent theta
now a third equation was mentioned in
that video and it's this one
y sub m times d
is equal to l
m times lambda
now you can only use this equation if
and only if theta is small
now as d decreases theta increases
so if the width of the slit is like very
small
you need to be careful because if the
angle is large
then this equation doesn't work
so in this example d is very very small
so we're not going to use that equation
but if d was like let's say 5
millimeters
that's large enough where
theta will be very small and we could
simply use that formula
that's theta one
and here we have
theta two and so forth
so you know what the angles are
this is y one with the first bright
fringe and this is y2
now let's talk about the single slit
experiment
so instead of two openings there's going
to be only one opening
and this is going to be the screen
let's tell the distance between the
screen
and
the other side
so this is the width of the slit which
is d
and the pattern is going to be different
in the middle we're still going to have
a very bright fringe
and then after that
there's not going to be
any significant bright fringes anymore
so at the first dark fringe that's where
m
is equal to one
and here m is equal to two
and then here m is equal to three
m is based on
the dark fringes or where destructive
interference occurs
so now let's focus on this problem
what is the width of the central maximum
in degrees centimeters
so this is the central maximum
so we need to calculate
this width right here
so let's focus on the top triangle
this here is y1
y1 is the distance between
the center
and the first dark fringe so that's y1
so the width that we're looking for
is basically twice the value of y1
so this is the width that we need to
calculate
that's going to be in meters
now we also want the angle
of the central maximum so let's say this
is theta one
so the angle that we want is really this
total angle or two theta one
so that's going to be the angular wave
so to speak
so if we can calculate theta 1 we can
calculate all of it
so let's focus on finding theta 1. and
this is l
so first let's use this equation d sine
theta
is equal to m times lambda
so d is two times ten to the minus six
m
m is one for the first dark french
and lambda is 680
times 10 to the minus 9 meters
so if we take 680 times 10 to the minus
9 and divided by 2 times 10 minus 6.
we can see that sine theta
is 0.34
so theta is going to be the arc sine of
0.34
and so theta 1 is
19.9 degrees if you round it
so that's a fairly large number
so we can't use that third equation
where theta is small
so the angular width
or the width of the central maximum in
degrees
is twice
this value
now the exact answer was like 19.877
for those of you who
don't want to round it
so the angular width is 39.75
degrees
and so that's the answer to the first
part of the problem
now let's move on to the second part
so we need to calculate
y1
so we could use this equation
y sub m is equal to l tangent theta m
so we're looking for y one l is
one point four meters
and we need to use theta one which is
nineteen point eight seven seven degrees
so y one is about point five zero six
two meters
and so this entire width represents
2y1
so the width is going to be
1.01 meters
and so that's the width of the central
maximum that's the answer to the second
part of the problem
let's work on another problem
light with a wavelength of 570
nanometers
shines on a single slit that is 7.5
meters away from the screen the width of
the central maximum is 3.2 centimeters
how wide is the slit
so let's start with a picture
so we have a single slit
let's say this is a screen
and so this is l
and this is d
and let's say this is the central
maximum
so our goal
is to calculate d
now we have the width of the central
maximum
so this right here is 3.2 centimeters
and if we draw a triangle
which i'm going to redraw here
this is y1 and this is l
and this is theta 1.
so the width of the central maximum is
twice the value of y1
so this is w and this is
y1 so you can visually see it
now let's make a list of what we know
so y1 is half of w
so 3.2 divided by 2 that's
1.6 centimeters
we have l which is 7.5 meters
we have lambda that's 570 nanometers
we don't know the angle and we don't
know d
so let's calculate the angle first
so let's use this equation y1 is equal
to l
tangent theta one
so y one is one point six centimeters
which is point zero one six meters
l
is seven point five meters
and so point zero one six divided by 7.5
that's equal to 0.00213
3 repeating
and so the angle is going to equal arc
tangent
of
this value
so the angle is small it's 0.122
meters
so now that we have the angle
we can calculate d
using this formula
d sine theta is equal to m times lambda
so this is going to be sine of that
angle 0.122
and m
is 1 because
we're dealing with central maximum only
so here the first dark fringe
will have a value of one
and lambda
that's
times 10 to negative nine
so it's 570 times 10 to the negative 9
divided by sine of 0.122
and so in this example d
is 2.68
times 10 to the negative 4
meters
so if we divide that by 10 to the minus
that's about 0.268
millimeters
now let's see if we can get the same
answer using the other formula since
theta is very small
and so that's this formula ym
times d
is equal to l times m times lambda
you can only use that if theta is small
so l is 7.5 our goal is to look for d
m is one
since the central maximum is bounded
by the first dark fringe on either side
and we have lambda
that's 570 nanometers
and ym or y1
is half of the width of the central
maximum so that's 1.6 centimeters
so now we could just use this formula
and get the answer
so ym or y1 is .016 meters
times d
l is 7.5 m is one and lambda is 570
times
10 to the negative nine
so let's multiply these first
and so on the right side
this is equal to 4.275
times 10 to the negative six
so then we need to divide both sides by
.016
and so the width of the slit
is two point
six seven times ten to negative four
meters so this answer is more exact
and if we divide that by 10 to the
negative 3
this is 0.267
millimeters
and so you get the same answer
if you use this equation or the other
one
actually the other one is probably more
exact because
this is based on
saying that sine theta is approximately
theta and also tangent theta
is approximately theta which is
basically true if theta is very very
small
you